<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A New and exact description of Moscovy (1.) containing its state antient and modern, situation, extent, latitude, division into provinces, rivers, soile, sterility, and fertility, with the commoditys, and observations on the extreamitys of weather hot and cold, (2.) of the citys and towns, fortification and manner of building ... (3.) of their religion, marriages, ... (4.) of the government ... (5.) their military affairs ... (6.) the revenues of the czar ... (7.) the succession of the royal house of Muscovy ... : the whole containing all that is necessary to be known concerning that vast empire.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52872</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N541</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38883</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18185817</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18185817</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106947</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52872)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106947)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1128:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A New and exact description of Moscovy (1.) containing its state antient and modern, situation, extent, latitude, division into provinces, rivers, soile, sterility, and fertility, with the commoditys, and observations on the extreamitys of weather hot and cold, (2.) of the citys and towns, fortification and manner of building ... (3.) of their religion, marriages, ... (4.) of the government ... (5.) their military affairs ... (6.) the revenues of the czar ... (7.) the succession of the royal house of Muscovy ... : the whole containing all that is necessary to be known concerning that vast empire.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Soviet Union --  Description and travel.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106947:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A <hi>New</hi> and <hi>Exact</hi> DESCRIPTION OF MOSCOVY.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Containing its <hi>State Antient</hi> and <hi>Modern, Situation, Extent, Latitude,</hi> Diviſion into <hi>Provinces, Rivers, Soile, Sterility,</hi> and <hi>Fertility,</hi> with the <hi>Commoditys,</hi> and Obſervations on the Extreamitys of Weather <hi>Hot</hi> and <hi>Cold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Of the <hi>Citys</hi> and <hi>Towns, Fortification</hi> and manner of <hi>Building.</hi> The firſt Diſcovery made by the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> Populouſneſs of the Country, <hi>Wild Beaſts,</hi> and <hi>Diſpoſition</hi> of the Natives.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) Of their <hi>Religion, Marriages,</hi> Obedience of the Wome<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to their Husbands, <hi>Divorce, Burials,</hi> and other Cerimonies. Their <hi>Diet, Liquors, Stoves, Hot-houſes, Habits,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) Of the <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Provinces</hi> and <hi>Shires,</hi> their <hi>Courts of Juſtice, holding Parliaments,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="5">(5.) Their <hi>Millitary Affairs, Degrees</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> in it, <hi>Arms, Diſcipline,</hi> with other matters.</p>
            <p n="6">(6.) The <hi>Revenues</hi> of the <hi>CZAR, Coins, Weights, Meaſurs, Trade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and of the <hi>Raritys</hi> of <hi>Moſcovy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">(7.) The Succeſſion of the <hi>Royal Houſe</hi> of <hi>Moſcovy</hi> to the preſent <hi>CZAR,</hi> being a <hi>Hiſtorical <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccount</hi> of all the <hi>Material Tranſact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions</hi> happening for 1600 years. The manner of the <hi>CZAR</hi>'s <hi>Coronation, Arms</hi> of <hi>Moſcovy,</hi> and Degrees of the <hi>Nobility,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The whole containing all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t is neceſſary to be known concerning that</hi> VAST EMPIRE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Baldwin,</hi> and Sold by mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Bookſellers,</hi> 1698.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:106947:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106947:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe following Sheets will Accomodate you with the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of ſurveying the Fam'd and Spacious Dominions of the Renowned <hi>CZAR</hi> of <hi>Moſcovy,</hi> in which you may rightly Inform your ſelf of all that is Rare or Admirable in that <hi>Northern Track,</hi> which for many Ages has been the Theatre of great Actions, and undergone divers notable Revolutions; a Country every where ſpoken of by <hi>Travellers,</hi> and a Trade or Commerce ſought with it eagerly by diſtant Nations. Here you have the State of things ſo Compact and Lively repreſented that theſe few Sheets cannot miſs of their end, in being exceeding Satisfactory, becauſe I may be bold to ſay, I have not omitted whatever can be reaſonably requir'd in ſuch an undertaking, even in the Minuteſt matters the Curious ſearchers after the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Remote Regions are apt to pry into, and thereby ſatiate their Curioſity with variety,</p>
            <p>I ſhall not trouble you with my Reaſons (as many too formally do on the like occaſions) for this undertaking, but rather leave you to your own Conjectures; yet one thing I cannot paſs over in ſilence, which is, that it may not prove only pleaſant in Reading, but very profitable and advantageous to ſuch as <hi>Trade,</hi> or may happen to <hi>Travel,</hi> in ſo large a part of the <hi>World,</hi> becauſe it contains ſomething of <hi>Hiſtory</hi> as well as diſcription, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weaving <hi>Antiquity</hi> with <hi>Modern</hi> ſpeculation, coſting no ſmall pains to produce ſo fair a birth, when ſuch ſlender accounts were to be had (from thoſe that have reſided there) to form it. It is true many Splendid <hi>Embaſſyes</hi> have been ſent and return'd in precedent <hi>Reigns;</hi> The underſtanding Men of our
<pb facs="tcp:106947:3"/> Nation have Travell'd there, and ſeen the face of that Earth <hi>Glaz'd with Snow in Winter,</hi> and in Summer found it <hi>Fruitful to Admiration,</hi> yet their enquiry has been but little into the State of Affairs, or the Produce of divers kinds, as not being ſufficiently Sedulous to inform themſelves and others; But here you will find the curtain drawn, and what lay long in obſcurity preſented by a larger Induſtry than what has before been undertaken, and ſo baniſhing all Scruples that may ariſe to prejudice yours or my Expation in the Succeſs of this Book; I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Friend and Servant,</hi> The Author.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106947:3"/>
            <head>A <hi>New</hi> and <hi>Exact</hi> DESCRIPTION OF <hi>Moſcovy,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of <hi>Moſcovy</hi> Antient and Modern: Its Situation, Extent, Diviſion into Provinces, Rivers, Soile, Latitude, Sterility and Fertility of the Fruits, Corn, and other Commodities it produces, with Obſervations on the Extream Cold and Heat Incident to this ſpacious Country, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>WE find by Experience, that God in his Infinite Wiſdom has Framed and Poſited the Globe of Earth and Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, with the Dependant Elements, ſo Admirable in every part, that Man cannot but be ſurpriz'd with wonder when he conſiders the Harmony in all the ſpacious Maſs, and his Curioſity would be tired with a too tedious ſearch into every particular. Let it ſuffice then that Modern Diſcoveries have brought to light, what former Ages knew little (or were altogether Ignorant) of. I ſhall not inſiſt on the <hi>American,</hi> or New World (ſo termed by many) That, but a few Ages paſt, all Europe, and, I may with reaſon ſay, the then two other Diviſions of the Suppos'd Total Univerſe were ſtrangers to; for, my bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs at preſent not lying that way, I ſhall bend it on the vaſt Northern Track of Country, antiently hinted at, and now ſo well diſcover'd by the Name of <hi>Ruſſia;</hi> but more properly, to follow the Modern Writers <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſcovy,</hi> as the far nobler, and moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted Name of that part of Earth, producing great advantages to ſuch as Trade with it, and an Improvement of Knowledge to thoſe that Travel its Spacious Limits.</p>
               <p>The Famed Country of <hi>Muſcovy,</hi> or as ſome will have it <hi>Ruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> is bounded on the Eaſt with the River <hi>Ob,</hi> or <hi>Oby,</hi> and the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106947:4"/> 
                  <hi>Negayan Tartars;</hi> on the Weſt with <hi>Lithuania, Livonia</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and;</hi> on the North with <hi>Lapland</hi> and the Ocean; on the South with a part of <hi>Tartary,</hi> called the <hi>Crimee:</hi> It was formerly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Sarmatia,</hi> and, as moſt ſuppoſe, changed its Name (becauſe it was divided into divers ſmall, but Abſolute Governments) to that of <hi>Ruſſia;</hi> for, in their Language the Word ſignifies a Part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or Dividing.</p>
               <p>VVhen this Country was called <hi>Sarmatia,</hi> it was divided into Two Principal Parts, the VVhite and Black. The firſt of theſe contain'd all that lyeth towards the North, and on the part of <hi>Liefland,</hi> viz. (as now the Provinces are nam'd) <hi>Vagha, Duyna, Vologda, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſtio, Carga, Polia, Novogrodia,</hi> and ſome others of leſſer note. As for the Black <hi>Sarmatia</hi> of the Antients, It comprehended the Southern part, toward the <hi>Euxine,</hi> or <hi>Black Sea,</hi> viz. The Dukedomes of <hi>Moſco, Volodemar, Rezan,</hi> and ſome others. Since this it has been enlarg'd by Addition and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, and is at preſent under a ſingle Government, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the Efforts the <hi>Tartars,</hi> and other bordering Countrys have made to hinder the flouriſhing of it, and to ſhare the Frontires amongſt them; to which end they have made Cruel Wars and Inroads, ſhedding much Blood, Plundering, Burning, and committing many othet Outrages.</p>
               <p>The Principal Provinces of <hi>Moſcovy</hi> (for ſo I muſt properly call it) are <hi>Volodemar, Moſcow, Pleſco, Niſnovogrod, Smolenſco, Novogrod-velica</hi> (or <hi>Novogrod</hi> of the Lower Country) <hi>Moſchora, Roſtove, Ghaletſa, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſtuga, Vagha, Cargapolia, Yaruſlave, Bealo, Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, Bezan,</hi> and <hi>Duyna.</hi> Theſe, with their Dependancies, are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Large, far exceeding our Shires in <hi>England;</hi> and though they are termed the Natural Provinces, there yet remain others gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Enlarging their Borders, viz. <hi>Twerra, Youghoria, Condora, Permia, Abdoria, Vedska, Boulghoria, Cheringo, Oudoria,</hi> comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Siberia, Cazan</hi> and <hi>Aſtracan,</hi> with ſome others now Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant on the Government of <hi>Moſcovy:</hi> So that this ſpacious Country, from North to South, Meaſur'd from <hi>Cola</hi> to <hi>Aſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can,</hi> which bends ſomewhat Eaſtward, is in Length a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 4260 Verſt, a Verſt being ſomething more than 3 quarters of an Engliſh Mile; and Northward beyond <hi>Cola</hi> are other Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories, but the Extream Cold is there very Oppreſſive, ſo that they are not much Fertil when their Coat of Snow is diſſolv'd by the Sun in the Four Hot Summer Months. The Breadth from that part which lyeth the fartheſt Weſt from the <hi>Narve</hi> ſide to the part of <hi>Siberia</hi> Eaſtward, is, in a manner, equal to the Length.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:106947:4"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſcovy</hi> is Water'd by many large Rivers, moſt of them, when the Weather is open being Navigable, ſome by leſſer and ſome by larger Veſſels that procure a conſiderable Trade, but in the Ridged Seaſon they are frozen over ſo that Sleads and Carriages paſs on them from place to place, they abound in Fiſh, and the <hi>Volga</hi> is famous for the great quantity of <hi>Sturgeon</hi> taken in it. It is about 2800 Verſt in length, an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Mile in moſt places over, and empties its Waters into the <hi>Caſpian</hi> Sea, running by <hi>Aſtracan,</hi> and other Towns of Note, to which it brings a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Trade. The other Rivers of Note, are the <hi>Boriſthenes,</hi> that divideth the Country from <hi>Lithuania,</hi> and falleth into the <hi>Euxine</hi> Sea. The <hi>Tanais,</hi> or <hi>Don,</hi> the Antient boundary be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Europe</hi> and <hi>Aſia,</hi> falling into the great Lake of <hi>Moeotis,</hi> by the City of <hi>Azou, Duyna</hi> falling unto the Bay of St. <hi>Nicholas,</hi> Northward, and to be brief, a great many more, as <hi>Moſcow</hi> running thorough the City of that Name, and about ten others very large, beſides ſmaller Streams, the leaſt for length and breadth comparable to the River of <hi>Thames;</hi> and from theſe proceed many Branches; ſo that take the Country in general, it is as well Watered as can be deſired, and accomodated with ſeveral good Ports and Havens.</p>
               <p>The Soile of this Spacious Country cannot be reaſonably ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, no more than others, Fertil in all places alike, and in ſome parts particularly, by reaſon of its Northern Situation, lying from 33 to 69 degrees and ſome Minutes North Latititude: Yet is it wonderful to ſee how God has ordered things here to the Advantage and for the Subſiſtance of the Inhabitants. The Earth, for the moſt part, is of a ſlight Sandy Mould, but not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like for producing ſuch things as ſpring up Northwards, towards St. <hi>Nicholas</hi> and <hi>Cola,</hi> and North-Eaſt towards <hi>Siberia,</hi> there is an indifferent Sterility, the Country there being full of Deſarts and vaſt Forreſts, by reaſon of the extreamety of the Climate in the colder Seaſon; but from the <hi>Volga,</hi> which lyes almoſt 1700 verſt from the Port of St. <hi>Nicholas,</hi> down towards <hi>Moſcow,</hi> and ſo the Southern parts that border on the <hi>Crimee,</hi> that contains near the like ſpace, the Country is very Fruitful in the proper Seaſon, yeilding Paſture, Corn, Flowers, pleaſant Fruits, and Woods in great plenty; and ſo it is between <hi>Rezan</hi> and <hi>Novogrod</hi> that lyes South-Eaſt from <hi>Moſcow</hi> and other parts, as between <hi>Moſcow</hi> and <hi>Smolensko,</hi> that lyes South-Weſt towards <hi>Littuania;</hi> inſomuch that one would wonder to ſee the great alteration be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106947:5"/> Winter and Summer in <hi>Moſcovy.</hi> In the former the whole Country is cover'd by a continual falling Snow, that is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a yard or two in deepneſs in the Southern parts, but more exceſſive in the North; and the Cold is ſo extream, that the Rivers and other Waters are Frozen to a vaſt thickneſs, and this uſually continues for five Months, <hi>viz.</hi> from the beginning of <hi>November</hi> till towards the end of <hi>March,</hi> at what time the Suns warm beams returning, the Snow begins to melt away, which makes the face of the Country look very frightful, and the Ways on the Thaw, for a time unpracticable. But then, as it were, on a ſuddain, the face of Nature is chang'd (for though a little before Water thrown up in the Air would deſcend in Ice drops, and any Mettal graſped faſt in ones hand ſtick to the Skin and make it bliſter if taken abroad, and many People venturing too far were frozen to death in the Streets, and on their Jorneys in the Sleads.) Now the Woods (that are moſtly of Birch and Firr) give a pleaſing ſight, the Meddows and Paſtures look green and grow apace, variety of Flowers appear in the Fields, and the Birds make a pleaſing Harmony, the Nightingals there in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance have a clearer Note than with us, and this ſuddain growth of things proceeds from the Benefit of the Snow which lying ſo long keeps off the Rigour of the Froſt, and diſolving ſo thoroughly, drenches and ſoaks the Earth, that the Sun coming hot as it were on a ſuddain into a cold Climate, the Plants and Herbs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> find ſuch a Noriſhment that they ſooner ſhoot forth than in warmer Countrys; and indeed, conſidering the paſt cold, the heat is greater than uſually with us in <hi>June, July</hi> and <hi>Auguſt</hi> which produces ſtore of <hi>Aples, Pears, Plums, Cherrys</hi> Black and Red, a Fruit like a <hi>Musk-Mellion</hi> but more pleaſant in taſt; <hi>Cucumbers, Gowrds, Raſps, Strawberrys, Hurtle-berrys</hi> and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Berrys; alſo <hi>Wheat, Rye, Barley, Peaſe, Buskway, Pſnytha,</hi> taſting ſomewhat like <hi>Rice,</hi> and ſometimes they have ſuch plenty that Wheat is ſold at two <hi>Engliſh</hi> Pence a Buſhel, the <hi>Rye</hi> is ſow'd before the Froſt, all other Grain for the moſt part the beginning of <hi>May,</hi> but the Northern parts are uſually ſerved in a great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree by the Southern with Corn as being more Steril.</p>
               <p>This Country above others is noted for Rich <hi>Furs</hi> which they get by hunting divers creatures, as alſo <hi>Hides, Tallow, Wax, Honey, Flax, Hemp, Tar,</hi> and other valuable Commoditys.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:106947:5"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> 
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the Cities and Towns of <hi>Moſcovy,</hi> their Situation, Fortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Manner of Building. The Diſcovery of the North-eaſt Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage by the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> their Factory Setled at <hi>Arch-Angel,</hi> &amp;c. The Populouſneſs of the Country, conſidering the Waſts in it: The Danger of Wild Beaſts, and the Diſpoſition of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>OF the Creatures of this Country I ſhall Treat particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly in due place; But now purſuing the Method I propoſe to lay down, The next thing that offers is the Cities, Towns, and the like, that Adorn and Beautify the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and thoſe of Note are,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſcow</hi> the Metropolis, from which the Country at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſeems to take its Name, as that City does from the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, on whoſe Bounds it ſtands: It is about 12 Miles in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, and may contain about 41500 Families, Convents, Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and Chappels: The Houſes in general are built with VVood, Plaiſter'd with Mortar and Straw, done over with Lime brought from <hi>Smolensko,</hi> &amp;c. and then covered over with Boards and Bark of Trees, which renders them cooler in Summer, and warmer in VVinter, but ſubjects them more to Fire, of which they have had many Fatal Experiments; for <hi>An.</hi> 1571. The <hi>Tartars</hi> Burnt it, and in it deſtroy'd about 80000 Perſons. <hi>Anno</hi> 1611. the <hi>Polanders</hi> Fir'd it. <hi>Anno</hi> 1676. an Accidental Fire happen'd, and ſunk 5000 Houſes in the Conflagration: But ſince care has been taken to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>build thoſe Devaſtations, for the moſt part, and at preſent 'tis reckon'd among the Flouriſhing Cities of Europe, and Guards are appointed to prevent the Progreſs of that Raging Element as much as lies in them, for the future preſerving the Building.</p>
               <p>The Churches and Houſes of the Perſons of Quality are Built with Stone and Brick; ſome of the Principal Churches Cover'd with Guilt Copper, or Tin, and Adorn'd with many Large Globes of the ſame Mettal. There is a Bell Raiſed on a Tower, I conceive the Largeſt in the World,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106947:6"/> for it is held to Weigh 176 Tun, though it has been Clip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, and ſome Tuns of Mettal taken from it to make it ſound the better, it is 24 Foot in height, and the Clapper 21 Foot. By pulling the Clapper, and ſtriking againſt the ſides it is Rung on particular occaſions. The Form of this Great City is in a manner Round, with Three Strong Walls Circling the one within the other, the Streets lying between, whereof the Inmoſt Incloſure in the Heart of the City, is all accounted the <hi>CZAR,</hi> or Great Duke's Caſtle; and the River Accommodates it with a Sufficiency of Water, ſtore of Fiſh, and other Proviſions. The Caſtle is Four-ſquare, Situate on a Hill Two Miles about, with Brick-walls very high, and a vaſt Thickneſs; it has Sixteen Gates, and as many Bulwarks: The Chief Markets are kept here, and on the River, when it is Glaz'd with Ice, this River encloſes the Caſtle on the South-weſt-ſide, and in it are Nine Fair Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches with Guilt Spires.</p>
               <p>The next City of Note is <hi>Novograde,</hi> but not ſo Stately as <hi>Moſcow.</hi> The Houſes are Built with Timber Layed-in, and Faſten'd with Dents, or Notches; and ſo faſten'd together holds well. The Streets, in ſtead of Paving, are Planked with Firr, and other Timber very neatly, of which Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence has plentifully ſtor'd them, ſo that a Houſe may be Built for a very little matter, as 20 or 30 Rubbles. This City Boaſts of the Fam'd Story of the <hi>Scythian</hi> Bondmen, who Rebelling againſt their Maſters, and Seazing the City, their Effects, Wives, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in their Abſence, and Overthrowing them on their Return, in a Bloody Battel; were, at length, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs Diſcomfited and brought under by their Maſters coming upon them only with Horſe-whips, which put them in Mind of the Chain of Servitude they had ſo lately broken, and conſequently Terrifi'd them into Obedience; and, upon this Account they have a Coine bearing the Impreſſion of a Horſeman, ſhaking a VVhip at a Flying Slave, Currant all over <hi>Moſcovy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The other Citys of great note are <hi>Roſtove, Volodomar, Smolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sko, Pleſco, Yaruſlave, Vologda, Periſlave, Niſnovogrod, Aſtracan, Cargapolia, Columna, Vſtiue, Cazan, Golmigreo,</hi> and of theſe <hi>Aſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can, Yaruſlave,</hi> and <hi>Cazan,</hi> have the precedency by reaſon of their convenient Situation on the borders ſo commodiouſly near the <hi>Volga. Yaruſlave</hi> exceeds the reſt for (beſides the plenty of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106947:6"/> Paſture and Corn the Soile yeilds) it has a great Trade by the River, being pleſantly Situated on a high Bank overlooking it, and from its Situation it ſeems to take its Name, for that in the <hi>Ruſs</hi> Language ſignifies a fair Bank, though they boaſt it from <hi>Vlademira</hi> Surnamed <hi>Yaruſlave,</hi> who Marry'd the Daughter of <hi>Harold</hi> King of <hi>England,</hi> by the Mediation of <hi>Sueno</hi> the <hi>Dane, An.</hi> 1067. To theſe of Note I may add <hi>Vobsko</hi> and <hi>Smolen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ko,</hi> which in ſome meaſure, ſtand in competition with them; <hi>Vologda</hi> is a pretty large City taking its Name from the River that paſſes through it. It has a Caſtle in it walled with Brick and Stone and many Churches but moſtly built of Wood, and whereas there are two for a Pariſh, one is ſo contriv'd that it may be heated with Stoves in the Winter, it is a Town of much Trade though lying far from any Sea port.</p>
               <p>There are many conſiderable Towns, as <hi>Colmogro</hi> ſtanding on the River <hi>Duyna,</hi> which is a great Town though without Walls, the Building is ſomewhat ſcattering, and near the Bay of St. <hi>Nicholas</hi> (ſo called from an Abby ſeated there when the <hi>Engliſh</hi> made a diſcovery of this Country) ſtands <hi>Arch-Angel,</hi> where they have a Factory and convenient Buildings, which lyes in about 64 degrees North-Latitude, and on the Banks of the River <hi>Duyna</hi> ſtands the Caſtle; the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have likewiſe Lands hereabouts aſign'd them, and in this Cold part (ſo pleaſant is the Country when the Snow is cleared, which it is doing 2 Months, and then the Ground in 14 days is dry) the Graſs is ſoon knee deep; and in an Iſland in St. <hi>Nicholas</hi> Bay 7 or 8 Miles in <hi>Circuit,</hi> called <hi>Roſe Iſland,</hi> grow Damask and Red Roſe, Violets, Wild Roſemary and other pleaſant things, ſo that to be brief I cannot but conceive this Country as to its many Waſts and Barren places, has been Miſrepreſented, and perhaps by ſome envious Neighbours becauſe the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had the Honour and Advantage firſt to diſcover the North-Eaſt Paſſage by Sea, which was done by one <hi>Chancelour</hi> an <hi>Engliſhman, Anno.</hi> 1553 Sir <hi>Hugh Willoughby</hi> and others miſcarrying in that tedious and painful Search; but ſince it has been eaſiy and Practicable, not only to us but other Nations: The <hi>Engliſh</hi> above others have found Encouragement upon the account of their being the firſt diſcoverers, for before the trade lay thorough <hi>Poland</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Hoſtil Territories. But not to make any long digreſſion I ſhall proceed in my intended Brevetie.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:106947:7"/>
               <p>This Country conſidering its largeneſs is well Peopled, where the huge Lakes and Deſarts take not up the ſpaces, and Woods render it Impracticable, yet theſe are advantageous to them in afoarding ſtore of Fiſh, Fowl and wild Beaſts, that yeild the Natives great advantage, their Fleſh for Food, and their Skins, Feathers, Tallow, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for Merchandiſe; the Lakes are very large, moſt of them Navigable, but not very commodious to live near by reaſon of great Fogs and Damps that ariſe from them, and as for Towns and Villages near the great Forreſts and Woods, the Inhabitants muſt be in ſome apprehenſion of danger from the great number of <hi>Wolves</hi> and <hi>Bears</hi> that Rove about for Prey, which Ravenous Creatures pinch'd in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive rigour of Winter with cold and hunger, contemning the fear of Dogs or Fire-Arms, will come out in Troops, and make a fearful havock among the People and their Cattle.</p>
               <p>The Natives of this Country are very induſtrious and Patient of Hunger, yeilding a profound Homage and Reſpect to their Prince, paying their Taxes with a willing and chearful obedience, and run readily to the Wars on the firſt command or ſummons; where it is ſtrange to ſee what hardſhip they will endure, for when the ground is cover'd with Snow frozen very thick, the common Soldier will lye in the Field without a Tent or cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over his head, only he hangs up his Mantle againſt that part from whence the Weather drives, and kindling a little Fire lyes down before it, his Food <hi>Oatmeal</hi> or <hi>Pulſe,</hi> and his Drink the cold Stream, his Horſe feeding on green Wood and Bark, and yet do the Service of the War, or Travel as well as thoſe that are Pamper'd in Stables with more convenient Provender, tho the Horſe has no other Covering than the Canopy of Heaven; and thoſe Soldiers that bear hardſhip the beſt, and deſerve well by Memorable Exploits, are rewarded ſometimes with Money, and at others with certain Lands Aſſigned them during Life, which the <hi>CZAR</hi> of <hi>Moſcovy</hi> always has in his Donation in one part or other of his Country for this purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:106947:7"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> 
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of their <hi>Religion, Wooing, Marriages.</hi> The <hi>Moſcovit</hi> Womens <hi>Obedience</hi> to their <hi>Husbands. Divorce, Burial</hi> of the <hi>Dead,</hi> and other <hi>Ceremonies.</hi> Their <hi>Feeding, Diet, Liquors, Stoves, Hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, Habits</hi> of <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Women,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THeir Religion properly is that of the <hi>Greek Church,</hi> dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering in many things from the <hi>Roman</hi> and <hi>Reformed Churches;</hi> their Service is in their own Language; they Receive the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> in both Kinds, obſerve Four Lents, and have Service Daily in their Churches. They have many Monaſteries Poſſeſs'd by Monks and Fryars, which have conſiderable Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues in Land and Houſes belonging to them, and likewiſe deal in Merchandiſe: When two Friends meet in the <hi>Eaſter</hi> Holy Days, they, in a Solemn manner, joyn Hands, one of them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſaying, <hi>The Lord is Riſen:</hi> Then the other Anſwers, <hi>It is ſo of a Truth,</hi> and then they Kiſs. They have a Metropolitan, or Patriarch, who is in High Eſtimation among them, and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renc'd as the <hi>Pope</hi> among the <hi>Roman Catholicks;</hi> they have a Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration for our <hi>Lady,</hi> St. <hi>Nicholas,</hi> and other Saints.</p>
               <p>Their manner of Wooing is but ſhort; for when they make Love, the Man ſends Preſents to the Woman, and ſhe Accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, the Match is ſoon Agreed; but if they are return'd, it is a ſign ſhe likes not the Party that makes the Proffer; and among other Preſents ſometimes a Whip is ſent, to let the Woman know what ſhe has to truſt to if ſhe be diſobedient, or break her Marriage Vows; and for the generality, they are ſo far from reſenting it as an Affront, that when Marry'd, the Wife Loves her Husband the better if ſometimes he Corrects her; and concludes, he Loves her not, if he altogether declines it: But this prov'd fatal once to an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Shoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker, who Marrying a <hi>Ruſs</hi> Woman, and ſettling in that Country, thinking to gain her Love to a high pitch this way, upon being inform'd that her peeviſhneſs proceeded from the want of it, he ſo Over-loaded her with his Kindneſs, that ſhe dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for which he loſt his own Life by the hand of an Executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner. The Women indeed are very Obedient to their Husbands, and the better ſort eſpecially ſeldom ſtir abroad but on parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106947:8"/> occaſions— And now as to their Marriages, becauſe the Ceremony is Novel to us, I ſhall mention the moſt parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular matters relating to it.</p>
               <p>The Day being come, the Bride puts on her Head a kind of a Hood made of fine Lawn, or Knit-work, that Veiles her to the Middle, and ſo with her Friends and the Bridegroom with his, they go to the Church on Horſe-back, though it be near at hand. They Marry with a Ring, and the words of Contract and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony much agrees with ours. The Ring put on, and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract Pronounc'd, the Brides hand is deliver'd into the hand of the Bridegroom, ſtanding this while on one ſide of the Altar, or Table, and the Bride on the other. The Knot being thus Knit by the Prieſt, ſhe comes about with the Bridegroom to the end of the Table, and falling down at his Feet, knocks her head up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Shoo, in token of Subjection and Obedience; then the Bridegroom caſts the Lap of his Gown over her, ſignifying his Duty to Protect and Cheriſh her. Then the Brides Father and Friends Bow to the Bridegroom, and his to the Bride, in token of Love and Affinity between the Two Kindreds. This done, the Bridegroom's Father delivers the Prieſt a Loaf of Bread, who preſently returns it, upon a Solemn Promiſe that the Dowry ſhall be deliver'd at the Day Appointed, and that Friendſhip ſhall continue between one Kindred and another: ſo the Bread is broken, and they eat it amongſt them, to teſtifie their True and ſincere Meaning for performing the Charge and Promiſe, and thenceforth to become as Crums of one Loaf, or Men of one Table.</p>
               <p>They uſe <hi>Divorce</hi> among them, and it is often practic'd on ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretences. For a Man may go to a Monaſtery and ſhave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Friar, in a Pretended Devotion, and Quit himſelf of his Wife, and leave her to her Shifts. Yet this is moſtly among the Vulgar, the Women of Quality are held in more Eſteem, yet without diſtinction they are very obedient, and pay a profound Reſpect to their Husbands.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Burials</hi> of their Dead, it is done with much Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony. They put them on New Shooes, and put a Letter in their Hands Directed to St. <hi>Nicholas,</hi> intimating the Party to be a <hi>Ruſs-Man,</hi> or <hi>Woman,</hi> dying in the True Faith: when the Ground is Frozen that no Spade can enter it, they lay up their Dead in Houſes, which they call God's Houſes, and when the Ground is practicable, they bury them in their Cloaths, cauſing Prayers to be ſaid over them; and beſide the Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106947:8"/> there are other Women Mourners, who are employ'd to that purpoſe. They have Great Veneration for the <hi>Croſs, Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> and <hi>Holy Water;</hi> once a year the <hi>Rivers</hi> are Hollow'd with much Ceremony by the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and then there is Great Strugling among the People for the Water, and ſome leap into it, though in a bitter Seaſon, and Women Dip their Tender Infants, conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding there is now a Great Vertue in it; and often it is Given to the Sick in order to recover them, or cleanſe them.</p>
               <p>They keep many <hi>Vigils,</hi> and other days ſet apart, and are very Zealous in their way of Worſhip; their Patriarch wears a Globe on his Mitre, ſeeming to ſignifie his Univerſality over the Church. In their Religious Worſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They uſe a great many Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, too many here to enumerate; The vulgar ſort little affect Learning, and are not much knowing in the Affairs of other Countrys, bending their Studyes or Induſtry on Tillage, Handicrafts, and other Inferiour Offices, little affecting Travel, though their Merchants Journey and Trade in divers Countrys of <hi>Europe</hi> and <hi>Aſia,</hi> having great advantage in the Latter by reaſon of the Commodious Situation of the <hi>Caſpian</hi> Sea, into which the River <hi>Volga</hi> carrys them, falling with ſuch violence that it keeps its ſtream for ſome Leagues in the Salt Water.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Moſcovits</hi> are generally very Burley, much affecting a Plump Fleſhy Corpulency, and this may happen by reaſon of their feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which they do very plentifully among the better ſort, and ſuch as are able to keep Good Tables, though their Diet is rather much, than over-curious. They commonly begin with a <hi>Chark,</hi> or Small-Cup of <hi>Aquavitae,</hi> which they call <hi>Ruſs-wine,</hi> and after that drink not till toward the end of Meals, and then they are not ſparing. They have variety of Diſhes, the firſt are their Bak'd Meats, for Roaſt-meat they little affect, and then their Brothes or Pottage; After Dinner they uſually ſleep on Benches The Drink of the Better ſort is <hi>Mead,</hi> but the poorer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> content with a thin Drink, call'd <hi>Quas,</hi> not exceeding our Small Beer, which many Drink. The Women are moſtly of Groſs Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and not ſo comely as in many <hi>European</hi> Countrys; Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore knowing their Natural Defect, to be the more B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lov'd of their Husbands, they uſe Art to mend their Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>exions, but their Paint and Waſhes are eaſily diſcern'd, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> being the Faſhion, it is rather Commended than Reprov'd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d the Husbands Allow their Wives and Daughters a comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> to buy Red and White Colours to this purpoſe; but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:106947:9"/> the heat of their Stoves, which are almoſt in every Houſe, much drys and wrinkles them, making them look old before they arrive to it; and for their Health, or rather to preſerve it, they uſe Bath-ſtoves, or Hot-Houſes commonly twice a week. Their Houſes, by heating their <hi>Peaches,</hi> which are made like <hi>German</hi> Bath-ſtoves, and their <hi>Potlads,</hi> like Ovens, are never without a conſiderable heat, though many times they will come out of them Sweating, and ſometimes plundge into the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter when they are foaming-hot, which would certainly kill any but thoſe that have Innur'd their Bodies to the two ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treameties of Heat and Cold, which few or no other Nations do, equal to them.</p>
               <p>As for their Habits, they are generally after the <hi>Greek</hi> Faſhion. The better ſort go decently and very Richly clad, and their Habit in ſome meaſure ſhows a diſtinction of degrees by ſome or other little variation. They ſhave their heads cloſe, unleſs fallen under the Princes diſpleaſure, and then let the hair grow as a Mark of dejectedneſs or Sorrow ſo to have offended as to be out of favour; but their Garments differ in Stuffs, though little in faſhion; the Women affect Rich ones as well as the Men, as Cloath, Rich Furs, Silks, Cloath of Gold, or Interwoven with it, and uſually down to their Ancles or Heels, though their Summer Garments are much lighter than thoſe they wear in Winter, the latter being always well lin'd with coſtly Furs, as <hi>Black Fox, Ermin, Martin, Grey, Squirel,</hi> &amp;c. of which Creatures, and many others yeilding Furs, they have abundance in the ſeveral Provinces. But the <hi>Mouſic</hi> and his Wife go meanly clad, yet will not be out of Court Faſhion as near as may be; their upper Garments are Courſe Cloath, and their under ones perhaps Sheeps Skin with the Wool on, though ſo dreſs'd that they are very warm and plyable; but this is for Winter, for in the Summer the Man goes in his Shirt and the Woman in a Linnen Garment, called two Shirts. Thus as I hope having given a Satisfatory account of this matter I proceed to others—</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:106947:9"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> 
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the Goverment of the <hi>Provinces</hi> and <hi>Shires.</hi> The <hi>Courts</hi> of <hi>Judicature.</hi> Their <hi>Jurisdictions,</hi> and the manner of Proceeding in them. Of the <hi>Chief Aſſembly,</hi> or <hi>Parliament.</hi> Their <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>HAving proceeded thus far in Generals and Particulars Relateing to <hi>Moſcovy,</hi> I now come more cloſely to the latter, as to what remains more Materialy to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd; and firſt of the Government of the Provinces and Shires, of this large Dominion.</p>
               <p>They are properly divided into four parts, which they call <hi>Chetfirds,</hi> or <hi>Tetrearchies,</hi> every part contains divers Shires, and is anex'd to the ſeveral Offices from whence it derives the Name.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Firſt</hi> beareth the name of <hi>Poſoskoy Chetfird,</hi> or the Jurisdiction of the Office of Ambaſſages, and the ſtanding Salary to the Officer is yearly 100 <hi>Rubbles</hi> or <hi>Marks,</hi> beſide great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages accruing.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Second</hi> is called <hi>Roſeradney Chetfird,</hi> becauſe it is proper to the <hi>Roſerade,</hi> or High Conſtable, who has a like Sallary with the former.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Third</hi> is <hi>Pomeſlenoy Chetfird,</hi> as appartaining to that Office; and here is kept a Regiſter of all the Lands given by the Prince for ſervice to his Noblemen, Gentlemen, and others. This Office giveth out and taketh in all the Aſſurances for them, and the Chief Officer has 500 <hi>Rubbles per Annum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Fourth</hi> is called <hi>Caſſanskoy-deworets,</hi> as being apropriated to the Office which has the Jurisdiction of the Kingdoms of <hi>Aſtracan</hi> and <hi>Cazan,</hi> with the Cities and Towns lying on the <hi>Volga,</hi> and is ſtipen'd at 150 <hi>Rubbles per Annum,</hi> and from the Jurisdiction of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Offices, but a very few places are priveledg'd, or exempted, except the <hi>CZAR</hi>'s Inheritance, or <hi>Vochin,</hi> as they call it; for that it pertained from antient time to the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106947:10"/> Houſe of <hi>Beala.</hi> This ſtandeth of 36 Towns, with their Bounds or Teritories, and ſome other particular Royaltie: Theſe great Officers reſide at Court, and carry their Offices with them where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they go: They receive all Complaints and Actions that are brought out of the ſeveral <hi>Chetfirds,</hi> and <hi>Quarters,</hi> to exhibit them to the <hi>CZAR</hi>'s Council and ſend back, and to ſend direction to thoſe that officiate under them in the Provinces for all matters given in charge by the Prince, or his Council, to be done or put in Execution within their precincts; and each of the Dukes of lower Nobility in head Towns, hath in Commiſſion with him a <hi>Dyack</hi> or Secretary to aſſiſt and adviſe him the better to Regulate and order matters as they fall out, and are directed, and their Commiſſion is to this Effect, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">(1.) To Hear and determine all Civil matters between Man and Man, and to that purpoſe have under them many Subſtitute Officers.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) They have Cognizance of all Criminal matters, as Theft, Murther, Treaſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but there lyes an Appeal from them to the <hi>CZAR</hi>'s Council; and though they take the Evidence in this caſe, they muſt draw up the Evidence and Information of the cauſe, and ſend it ready digeſted to the Officer of the <hi>Chetfird</hi> whereunto the Province belongs, by whom it is prefered and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to the Council; for they are not to determine Criminal matters, or do Execution on the offender without the Councils order.</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) If within the Province there be any publick Service re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd, as the Publiſhing of a Law, or Common Order, by way of Proclamation, Muſtering Soldiers, Collecting Taxes or Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it is proper to them.</p>
               <p>Theſe Dukes and <hi>Dyacks</hi> are appointed by the <hi>CZAR</hi> but for a year, and then at his pleaſure he may change them; which is uſually done, unleſs by Merrit or Interceſſion any are continu'd Longer; and though their higheſt Sallary is but 100 <hi>Rubbles per Annum,</hi> yet coming bare into theſe places, in one year they very much inrich themſelves.</p>
               <p>For ordinary matters, there are many other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fficers that hold Inferiour Courts, and otherways look after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e affair, not much differing in the main from what is practic'd in <hi>England,</hi> ſo that the Provinces are carefully regarded, and known Bribery is ſever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly puniſhed.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:106947:10"/>
               <p>As for the Courts of Civil Juſtice in <hi>Moſcovy</hi> for matters of Contract, and others of like ſort, beſide the former they are of three kinds, and by way of Appeal one is ſubjected to the other; the loweſt of theſe appointed for the Eaſe of the Subject, is the Office of the <hi>Gubnoy Staruſt,</hi> which ſignifies in their Language an <hi>Alderman,</hi> and of the <hi>Solsky Staruſt,</hi> or <hi>Baylif</hi> of the <hi>Soak,</hi> or <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred;</hi> theſe have power to determine matters within their <hi>Soaks</hi> or <hi>Hundreds</hi> under the Dukes and <hi>Dyacks</hi> of the Province before whom the Cauſes may be remov'd if not agreed or determin'd.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is held in the head Towns of the Provinces, Shires, before the Deputies of the Lords of the <hi>Chetfirds,</hi> and from theſe they have a Priviledge to Appeal or remove their Cauſes to the Third or Chief Court held at <hi>Moſcow,</hi> where uſually reſide the Officers of the <hi>Chetfrids.</hi> Theſe are the Chief Juſtices or Judges, every one of them in Civil Matters, that ariſe within their ſeveral <hi>Chetfird</hi> or Quarter; and may be either commenc'd originaly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, or proſecuted out of the Inferiour Courts of the Shires by way of Appeal.</p>
               <p>Their Commencing and Proceeding in Civil Actions is in this wiſe; The Plantif delivers his Supplycation, wherein he ſets forth the Merrit of his Cauſe, or wrong done to him; then, if alow'd, a <hi>Reepis</hi> or Warrant is granted, which he delivers to the <hi>Preſtave</hi> or Serjeant, who hereupon Arreſts the Defendant who muſt put in Suretie to Anſwer or elſe be kept in Cuſtody, and often on this account loaden with Irons; when they come before the Judg, the Plantif pleads his own Cauſe, and the Defendant make his Defence; as for Attorneys and Councellours they are not known in theſe Courts, when the Evidence, if they have any, is heard, Judgment is given, but if the matter remains doubtful, then the Judge demandeth of either party, whom he thinks ſit, whether he will kiſs the <hi>Croſs</hi> upon that which he denyeth or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voucheth; and he who conſents to do it is carry'd by an Officer to the Church, where he does it in a devout manner, and this is held a very Sacred Oath; and hereupon if it be the Defendant he is declar'd free of the Debt, paying 20 pence charges; but if both demand this priveledg, then they draw Lots, and he that has the beſt is only alowed it; and thus by ſhort proceeding with a little charge the Controverſy is ended; but if the Defendant be condem'd and not able to pay, his caſe is miſerable.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding all I have ſay'd of theſe Courts, there is yet another ſuperiour to them; and this is call'd <hi>Zabore,</hi> or the Publick Aſſembly, which properly is term'd a Parliament. The States and Degrees of Perſons that are preſent, are, 1. The <hi>CZAR.</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:106947:11"/> 2. The Nobility of Council. 3. The Clergy, for I do not find the Commons have any peculiar Repreſentatives in this <hi>Zabore,</hi> or <hi>Parliament,</hi> which is held briefly after this manner.</p>
               <p>The Prince cauſes the Nobility to be ſummon'd together, with the <hi>Patriarch,</hi> who Convocates his <hi>Clergy,</hi> viz. the two <hi>Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites,</hi> or <hi>Arch-Biſhops,</hi> with other <hi>Biſhops, Abbots</hi> and <hi>Friers,</hi> as are moſt Learned, and of beſt repute: Theſe aſſemble in the Court at <hi>Moſcow,</hi> and then the day is appointed when the Seſſions ſhall begin.</p>
               <p>The day being come, the Clergy Aſſemble before, ſitting at a place call'd the <hi>Stollie,</hi> and when the <hi>CZAR</hi> approaches with his Nobility then all the Clergy ariſe, and bowing themſelves, paſs on with their <hi>Patriarch</hi> to meet him. Then the <hi>Patriarch</hi> bleſſeth him with his two Fingers, laying them on his Forehead, and the ſides of his Face, then he Kiſſes him on the Right-ſide of his Breaſt.</p>
               <p>Theſe Ceremonies ended, they paſs to the <hi>Parliament-houſe,</hi> which is not very ſtately, and there they place themſelves in this order, The <hi>CZAR</hi> Seats him in a Throne on one ſide the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and not far from him is a little ſquare Table, and at it ſit the <hi>Patriarch</hi> with the Chief of his <hi>Clergy,</hi> and <hi>Principal Nobility</hi> of the Council; alſo two <hi>Dyacks,</hi> or <hi>Secretaries,</hi> call'd <hi>Dumnoy Dyacks,</hi> who write down what paſſes, or is to be Enacted. The reſt take their places on Benches that Encompaſs the Chamber.</p>
               <p>Being plac'd in this order, one of the <hi>Dumnoy Dyacks,</hi> who repreſents a Speaker, declares the cauſe of the Aſſembly, and Propounds, as he has it in Writing, the Principal Matters they are to proceed on, and the points being open'd, the <hi>Patriarch</hi> and his <hi>Clergy</hi> have the Priority of ſpeaking, and giving their Opinions or Advice; but they uſualy, out of a kind of Modeſty, refuſe it, and deſire, theſe things, being matters of State, and other ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to the Common-wealth, that the <hi>CZAR</hi> and his <hi>Nobles,</hi> who are more knowing and learned therein, would order theſe weighty Affairs, whilſt they that are Church-men would aſſiſt them with their Prayers, and ſo one by one they anſwer to that Effect. After this, the matters propounded are agreed to ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times entire, and at others with little variation; for without much difficulty every one gives his conſent. Then the Clergy take their leaves, bleſſing the <hi>CZAR,</hi> who conducts the <hi>Patriarch</hi> to the next Room, and then returns to his Seat, till things are prepar'd for his return to his Pallace.</p>
               <p>The Acts that paſs in this manner, the <hi>Dyacks,</hi> or <hi>Secretaries</hi> draw up into form of <hi>Proclamation,</hi> which are ſent, and directed to be Publiſh'd in the Provinces and head Towns by the <hi>Dukes</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:106947:11"/> and <hi>Dyacks</hi> or <hi>Secretarys</hi> of thoſe places, and ſo the Seſſions ended, after a Splendid Entertainment, every one has leave to depart.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the <hi>Millitary Affairs</hi> of <hi>Moſcovy,</hi> the Degrees and Order of the Soldiers, Officers. Their Abilities and Warlike Diſcipline, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things at Large relating to Martial Enterprizes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe next thing I ſhall Treat of is the Millitary Affairs of <hi>Moſcovy,</hi> which is a thing very well worth noting; and firſt of their Forces for the War, and Chief Officers.</p>
               <p>The Soldiers are call'd <hi>Sinabojarsky,</hi> or the Sons of Gentlemen, being all, or moſtly of that Degree, by virtue of their Military Profeſſion; for when they are of years to bear Arms, they come to the <hi>Reſerade,</hi> or Great Conſtable, who, at their requeſt, enters their Names, alotting them a Maintainance to ſupport their Charge, there being Lands Aſſigned for this purpoſe, annexed to this Office, which cannot be Alienated, ſo that there is, as I may term it, a Succeſſion of Soldiers, and uſually the whole number in continual Pay is as followeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt.</hi> The <hi>Dworany,</hi> or <hi>Penſionary-Guards</hi> of the Princes Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who are 15000 Horſemen, with their proper Officers, and are always in Readineſs; but of theſe there are Three Degrees, who differ as well in Eſtimation, as Wages, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Dworany-Bulſhey,</hi> or Head-Penſioners. The <hi>Serendany Dworany,</hi> or the Middle-Rank of Penſioners. The <hi>Dyta Boiarsky,</hi> or the Lower Rank. Theſe have from 100 to 20 <hi>Rubbles per Annum,</hi> leſſening according to their Station; one half is payed at <hi>Moſco,</hi> and the other by the General in the Field; beſides this, they have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable Lands Alloted them, from the greateſt to the leaſt.</p>
               <p>There are other Horſemen, to the number of 110, much like the <hi>Roman Praetorian</hi> Soldiers, who have the more immediate care of the <hi>CZAR</hi>'s Perſon when he goes the Wars, all of ſpecial Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for their Truſt and Nobility, which he chuſes himſelf, and cauſes their Names to be Regiſtred; and for their Large Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues in Penſion-places, they are to bring to the Wars 65000 Horſemen, with their Furniture and other Neceſſaries; and once a Year, if there be no Wars, they are to make their Appearance on the <hi>Tartar</hi> Frontiers, ſo there ſeldom fails of being 80000,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106947:12"/> a few more or leſs, when they are requir'd to take the Field; and greater Forces are ſpeedily Raiſed on any occaſion out of the ſupernumerary <hi>Sinabojarsky,</hi> that are not in Pay till call'd upon neceſſary occaſions, and all willingly flock to the Regal Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard, upon the firſt Notice; and if a competent number be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Noblemen that hold Lands of the Crown, are to make them up with their Servants and Tenants, call'd <hi>Colophey,</hi> which when the Service is over, lay down their Weapons, and return to their Servil Occupations. Over and above the Horſemen menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd, there are ſeldom leſs than 12000 Foot in Pay, that bear Fire-Arms, or Gunners, called <hi>Strelſeys,</hi> and theſe are appointed to their ſeveral Poſts, ſome to Guard the City of <hi>Moſco,</hi> and the Pallace, others are diſpos'd of in Garriſons till there be further occaſion for them. There are likewiſe in his Service a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent number of Strangers, and theſe are <hi>Europeans</hi> of divers Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, being chiefly employ'd againſt the <hi>Tartars.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Commanders in Chief of theſe Great Forces are the <hi>Voya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vod Bulſhaia,</hi> Great Captain, or Lieutenant-General under the <hi>CZAR,</hi> uſually choſen out of the Four Houſes of the Chief Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; he has joyn'd with him Lieutenant Generals of great Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience. Beſide, there are Four Officers that have the Marſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Army divided among them, call'd Marſhals of the Field, every one hath his Quarters or fourth part. The firſt is call'd <hi>Prava Polskoy,</hi> or the Right-wing, the ſecond is <hi>Levoy Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skoy,</hi> or the Left-wing. The third <hi>Ruſnoy Polskoy,</hi> or the broken Band, becauſe there are Detachments made from it on any neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary occaſion. The fourth <hi>Storeſhovoy,</hi> or the Warding Band; Theſe have each Two Marſhals under them, who are to Muſter and Train the Soldiers, and do Juſtice on Offendors; and theſe are commonly choſen out of the 110 I have before mention'd. They receive and deliver Pay to the Army; under them are the <hi>Gulavoy,</hi> or Captains of Thouſands, Five hundreds, and Hundreds. The <hi>Petydeſetskoy,</hi> or Captains of Fifty, and the <hi>Decetskiſs,</hi> or Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of Tens.</p>
               <p>There are, beſide the Lieutenant-General, two other <hi>Voiavods,</hi> one Maſter of the Ordinance, who hath divers under-Officers ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the Service, and the Walking-Captain, or Scouts-Maſter, who has under him 1000 Expert Horſemen to go out on Parties, and Spy the Enemy; ſo that a <hi>Moſcovite</hi> Army appears very Formidable: And indeed they have done many brave. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits, they have lately taken <hi>Aſoph,</hi> a very Important place, and the laſt Year, in a Set-Battel, Overthrown and Ruin'd a Great Army of <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars,</hi> going compleatly Armed, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106947:12"/> well underſtanding the uſe of Fire-Arms; Whereas formerly their Weapons were but ſlight, moſtly Bows and Arrows, Marching in good Order more than ever, as having learn'd the Art of War more perfectly from the <hi>Poles,</hi> and other Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Nations. They alſo Encamp, Entrench and Lodg Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geouſly, being very patient of Hunger, Thirſt and Cold, Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to their Officers, and Ready to Charge the Enemy on all occaſions. They had in uſe a Moving Caſtle, as they call it, which mainly defended them againſt the <hi>Tartars</hi> Arrows, and gave them a more ſecure Opportunity to Offend their Enemies. This was Fram'd Wood, carry'd on Numerous Carts, which, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Occaſion, was eaſily put together, and made a Standing Wall of Seven Miles, or as few as they thought fit, with Loopholes in it, to diſcharge their Shot, or dart their Arrows; but I am not well aſſur'd, whether they have ſo cumberſome a Machin now in uſe or not, for it is little or no defence againſt Great Artillery, which the <hi>Turks,</hi> Aſſiſting the <hi>Tartars,</hi> uſe. The <hi>Muſcovites</hi> are very Expert at Defending Garriſons, and are accounted there better Soldiers than in the Field; however by their Wars they have greatly Enlarg'd their Borders, almoſt on all ſides them; Eſpecially ſince they have entertain'd Expert Officers of divers Warlike Nations, who have, by their Experience and Valorous Examples, Cultivated and Animated the Soldiery; but not too tediouſly to dwell on this Particular. I'll now proceed to other Matters, as worthy of Note, ſo that taking altogether, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doubt but I ſhall give the <hi>Reader</hi> all the Reaſonable Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction he can deſire of a Country, that but a few Ages paſt we were in a manner Ingorant of.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> 
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Some Account of the Vaſt <hi>Revenues</hi> of the <hi>CZAR,</hi> by Cuſtoms, and other ways ariſing. The <hi>Coine, Weights, Meaſures,</hi> and other matters Relating to Trade. The ſtrange ſorts of <hi>Fiſh, Beaſts, Fowl,</hi> and other Rarities of <hi>Moſcovy.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe Cuſtoms and Revenues that Maintain ſo Great a Charge in War and Peace, are very conſiderable; and, by a few, one may gueſs at the reſt. That at <hi>Moſcow</hi> amounted to 12000 <hi>Rubbles</hi> Yearly; <hi>Smolensko</hi> 8000; <hi>Vobsko</hi> 12000; <hi>Novogrod-Veli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:106947:13"/> 6000; <hi>Sturrarouſe,</hi> by Salt, and other Commodities, 18000; <hi>Torſhock</hi> 800; <hi>Otfer</hi> 700; <hi>Yaruſlave</hi> 1200; <hi>Coſtrome</hi> 1800; <hi>Niſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Novogrod</hi> 7000; <hi>Caſa</hi> 11000; <hi>Vologda</hi> 12000: A <hi>Rubble</hi> is a <hi>Mark Engliſh.</hi> And thus ſtands the Antient Account, ſince the ſtating of which Trade is greatly encreas'd. Beſides this, the Province of <hi>Volsko</hi> pays yearly for <hi>Tagla</hi> and <hi>Podat</hi> 18000 <hi>Rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles; Novogrod</hi> 35000; <hi>Torſhock</hi> and <hi>Otſer</hi> 8000; <hi>Razan</hi> 3000; <hi>Morum</hi> 12000; <hi>Colmigroe</hi> and <hi>Duyna</hi> 8000; <hi>Vologda</hi> 12000; <hi>Cuzan</hi> 28000; <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſtiuga</hi> 30000; <hi>Roſtove</hi> 50000. The City of <hi>Moſco</hi> 40000; <hi>Siberskoy</hi> 20000; <hi>Caſtrome</hi> 12000.</p>
               <p>The former in the Citys are for Cuſtom, and theſe latter, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Tagla</hi> is a Yearly Impoſition, raiſed on every <hi>Wite</hi> or Meaſure of Grain within the Provinces, gather'd by <hi>Shozen-men;</hi> a <hi>Wite</hi> contains 60 <hi>Chetfrids,</hi> every <hi>Chetfrid</hi> is Three Buſhels En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, or little leſs. The <hi>Podat</hi> is an ordinary Rent, impos'd on every Hundred. There comes in a Vaſt Sum Yearly by the <hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin,</hi> or <hi>Crown-lands.</hi> The <hi>CZAR</hi>'s Inheritance containing 36 Large Towns, with their Territories, or Hundreds belonging, and a vaſt quantity of other Lands, that bring great Incomes to the Crown. The Tithes of <hi>Furs,</hi> and Cuſtoms on Goods, of Strangers by Navigation, or otherways, very much Encreaſe the Revenue, beſide other things and ways to Raiſe Money, too Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous to mention; and for theſe there are Offices and Officers reſpectively appointed, who have conſiderable Salarys, ſo that the Riches of this Large Northern Kingdom appears very great, and the Princes Vaſt Revenues very difficult to be Summ'd up: And ſince I am come to this part of Relation, I ſhall ſpeak briefly of the <hi>Coine, Weights</hi> and <hi>Meaſures,</hi> that are ſo neceſſary in Trade, and vary ſo much from ours, that ſo Merchants and Travellers may the better underſtand them, when their Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or Curioſity ſhall make them uſeful.</p>
               <p>The Merchants Accounts are kept at <hi>Moſcow</hi> the chief City divers ways, as by thoſe of <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>Rubbles</hi> and <hi>Pence,</hi> call'd by the <hi>Moſcovites Muscofskins,</hi> two hundred of them going to a <hi>Rubble.</hi> The <hi>Duthby Grevens</hi> and <hi>Muſcofskins,</hi> 20 of the latter going to the former, ſo 10 <hi>Grevens</hi> make the <hi>Rubble,</hi> which is held an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aginary Coine; for the Currant Mony is the <hi>Capeck</hi> worth a <hi>Stiver Flemiſh,</hi> and ſomething more in value than an <hi>Engliſh Peney,</hi> 10 of them make a <hi>Greven,</hi> 3 <hi>Capecks</hi> are call, d an <hi>Altine,</hi> by which Contracts and Bargains are uſually made; 33 <hi>Altines</hi> and one <hi>Capeck</hi> make a <hi>Rubble.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:106947:13"/>
               <p>At <hi>Arch-Angel</hi> there is an <hi>Exchange</hi> practic'd, and the Price of <hi>Ruſs</hi> Mony bears as the ſcarcety or plenty will allow. The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts begin in <hi>Auguſt</hi> to return in <hi>London</hi> about the latter end of <hi>December.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Weights chiefly in uſe, are the <hi>Pood,</hi> by which all fine Goods are weighed, as <hi>Beaver, Silk, Wool,</hi> &amp;c. but for groſs Goods they have a Weight call'd the <hi>Berzovet,</hi> accounted 10 <hi>Poods,</hi> or the <hi>Ruſsſhip-Pound,</hi> computed to be 360 Pound <hi>Averdupois;</hi> ſo that all Goods bought by this Weight are accounted to be 10 <hi>Per cent</hi> profit; ſo that many have recon'd Goods ſo bought to pay the Freight with over-weight, and all Goods bought by the <hi>Pood</hi> to be 10 <hi>Per cent</hi> leſs.</p>
               <p>The Meaſure of length is call'd the <hi>Archin,</hi> and is accounted 28 <hi>Engliſh Inches,</hi> ſo that 100 <hi>Archins</hi> are ſuppoſed to produce <hi>Incirca,</hi> 78 yards of <hi>London</hi> Meaſure, Oyle, moſtly Fiſh-Oyle, they ſell by the Barrel, each Barrel accounted half a Hogſhead. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cave Meaſures are little us'd in Trade; As for their Furs, of which they have many ſorts, as <hi>Bever, Otter, White, Red Black</hi> and <hi>Dun Fox, Sables, Martins, Minever,</hi> &amp;c. they are uſually ſold by the Timber Weight, or Tale, and much coveted by Merchant Strangers who purchaſe them at dear rates, and ſend them into moſt Countrys of <hi>Europe,</hi> and <hi>Aſia,</hi> and into the other parts of the World.</p>
               <p>They take upon the Coaſt abundance of <hi>Seals,</hi> which is done in this manner; they carry their Boats over the Ice to open Water, and finding their haunts where they lye basking on huge Flakes of Ice, in a Sunſhiney day coming out of the Sea for that purpoſe, they hem them in, with their Boats, and with great Clubs, ſtrik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them on the Noſe quickly kill them; their Skins are good Merchandice, and of their Fat they make a ſort of <hi>Rediſh Oyle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is another Sea-Creature called a <hi>Morſe,</hi> who has Teeth about a foot long, by the help of which he clambers up Rocks to ſeek for Prey, and for the ſake of his Teeth they take him, which exceeds <hi>Ivory,</hi> and are of great eſteem among them. They have in ſome parts of the Country <hi>White Fox, Grey</hi> and <hi>Red Squirrils,</hi> a large <hi>Water-Rat,</hi> whoſe Skin ſmells naturaly like <hi>Muske.</hi> They have alſo <hi>Wulberins:</hi> They have likewiſe a Beaſt called <hi>Loſh</hi> or <hi>Buff,</hi> whoſe Skin turns to very good account.</p>
               <p>They have a Fiſh called <hi>Ribzuba,</hi> whoſe Teeth are as fine as <hi>Ivory,</hi> and uſed for heads of <hi>Knives, Sword-hafts,</hi> &amp;c. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſome uſe the Powder to Antedote Poiſon, as the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorns
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106947:14"/> horne;</hi> this I hold to be the ſame with the <hi>Morſe:</hi> The word <hi>Ribzuba</hi> in their Language rather ſignifieing the Tooth than the Fiſh, for it is caught about <hi>Pecliora,</hi> or <hi>Petzora,</hi> ſome of them have been found with their Teeth of 2 foot long, weighing 11 Pound, or more. They have in the Woods and Mountains many wild <hi>Horſes,</hi> alſo flying <hi>Squirils,</hi> having <hi>Tufts</hi> of hair growing to their Shouldiers, like Wings, which makes them ſeem to fly when they take vaſt leaps from one Tree to another; their Tails are much broader than others, which ſhakes and ſpreads as they leap, and ſo facilitates them in their Agillity. They have <hi>Hares</hi> the colour of ours in Summer, but in Winter they change their Coats into <hi>Milk-white,</hi> and the <hi>Squirils</hi> the like, from a <hi>Rediſh</hi> unto a <hi>Grey,</hi> whereof cometh the <hi>Calaber.</hi> They have ſtore of <hi>Deer, Roe-Bucks</hi> and <hi>Goats,</hi> in ſome parts <hi>Elks</hi> on which the <hi>Semoids</hi> on their borders Ride, and cauſe their Sleads to be drawn by <hi>Harts,</hi> or <hi>Ollins</hi> large <hi>Dogs,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Their <hi>Horſes</hi> and <hi>Sheep</hi> are but ſmall, yet both good in their kind. As for Fowl, they have great plenty, as the <hi>Egle-Hawks</hi> of ſeveral kinds, The <hi>Swan</hi> Wild and Tame, the <hi>Stork</hi> and <hi>Crane,</hi> the <hi>Tedder</hi> of the colour of a <hi>Pheſant,</hi> but much biger, living in the Firr-woods: of <hi>Pheſant</hi> and <hi>Partridge</hi> they have great plenty. The <hi>Owls</hi> in <hi>Moſcovy</hi> are exceeding large, their Ears as big as a Man's, and much like them. They have many River-Fiſh common with ours, as <hi>Pike, Carp, Roaeh, Tench,</hi> &amp;c. but others altogether ſtrange to us, as the <hi>Behlouga</hi> or <hi>Bellougiva,</hi> 4 or 5 Ells long. The <hi>Severinga</hi> or <hi>Sterledy,</hi> ſomewhat in faſhion and taſt like a <hi>Sturgeon,</hi> but not ſo thick nor long. The <hi>Ribela</hi> or <hi>White Salmon,</hi> theſe are found in great plenty in the River <hi>Volga,</hi> and other Rivers; in a River near the Town of <hi>Periſlave</hi> they take a Fiſh, like our <hi>Herring,</hi> but not ſo big. They have abundance of <hi>Salt-wells</hi> turning to great advantage in making Salt, and near <hi>Aſtracan</hi> the Sea-Water being thrown up among the Rocks in the hot weather, the Sun makes it into Hills of Salt; they have in this Country a Lucid Slate cut out of a Rock, which being ſplit into thin ſlivers ſerves as Traſparent Glaſs, and in the Rivers near the Bay of St. <hi>Nicholas,</hi> ſeveral Rocks of <hi>Alablaſter;</hi> but not to wade too far in matters that to ſome may ſeem Trival, I intend to cloſe with what may yet ſeem more worthy of Note.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:106947:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> 
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Succeſſion of the Royal Houſes of <hi>Moſcovy</hi> for about <hi>1600</hi> years, to the preſent <hi>CZAR,</hi> giving an Hiſtorical account of their Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rys, Enlarging their Dominions, the Revolutions that have happen'd in the State. The manner of the Corronation, and other things of the like nature. The <hi>CZAR</hi> or great Duke of <hi>Moſcovys</hi> Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Titles. The Impreſs of the Broad Seal. Degrees of Nobility, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe Succeſſion of the Government of that vaſt Country now call'd <hi>Moſcovy,</hi> in part, and in the whole has been of Antient ſtanding, as will appear in the following brief Hiſtory, brought down to the preſent <hi>CZAR, Peter Alexo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Dukes</hi> of <hi>Moſcovy</hi> are held, though it may be thought ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing doubtful, from <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> the ſecond <hi>Roman</hi> Emperour; however according to other Hiſtorians Writing of this matter, I ſhall trace it from hence to an undoubted certainty, as the times came nearer to us, and briefly touch on what memorably happen'd by the way.</p>
               <p>They tell us that <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> ſent ſome of his near Kindred to be Governours in theſe Parts; and amongſt them one <hi>Pruſſus,</hi> who Named his Province or Government <hi>Pruſſia,</hi> which lay on the Eaſtern <hi>Baltic</hi> Shoar, by the River <hi>Wixel;</hi> of whom <hi>Rurek Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rianus,</hi> and <hi>Truvrio</hi> decending, by the fourth Generation, were by the <hi>Ruſſians,</hi> then living without Civil Government, ſent for <hi>Anno. Dom.</hi> 573 to bear Rule over them, at the perſwaſion of <hi>Goſtomiſlius,</hi> chief Magiſtrate of <hi>Novogrod;</hi> and taking with them <hi>Olechus</hi> their Kinſman, they had by common Conſent, the Government of thoſe Countrys divided amongſt them, and all but <hi>Rurek</hi> dying without Iſſue, <hi>Vorſon</hi> his Son ſucceeded him in the whole Government, as it had been Agreed amongſt them, who took to Wife <hi>Olba</hi> Daughter to a Citizen of <hi>Pleſco,</hi> who brought him a Son call'd <hi>Stoſlaus,</hi> who ſucceeded him, and was ſlain in Battel. He left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him 3 Sons, to wit <hi>Teropolehus, Olega</hi> and <hi>Volodimir.</hi> The latter ſupplanted the two firſt, and took the whole Government upon him, and Marry'd <hi>Anna</hi> Siſter to <hi>Baſilius</hi> the Eaſtern Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106947:15"/> and with all his People, in the year 988. was Baptiz'd, as Hiſtorians ſay, upon a Miracle perform'd by a <hi>Greek</hi> Biſhop, <hi>viz.</hi> his throwing the Book of the Goſpel into the Fire, and its re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining there a conſiderable time untouch'd by the force of that conſuming Element.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Volodimir</hi> left behind him 11 Sons, among whom he divided his Dominions; but <hi>Jaroſlaus</hi> one of them, by reaſon of a diviſion among them got the ſole Government into his hands; and <hi>Volodimir</hi> his Son ſucceeded him, holding his Court at <hi>Kiow</hi> on the River <hi>Boriſthenes,</hi> and had great Wars much enlargeing his Borders, and was the firſt that had the Title of <hi>CZAR,</hi> or <hi>Caeſar</hi> confer'd on him by <hi>Conſtan</hi> the <hi>Greek</hi> Emperour, who ſent him many Rich Gifts. After him in deſcent, were <hi>Vuſzevolodus, George, Demetrius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then <hi>George</hi> his Son, who in the year 1237 by <hi>Bathy</hi> a <hi>Tartar</hi> Prince, brought <hi>Moſcovy</hi> under his Subjection, making it Tributary to him; and the <hi>Ruſs</hi> ſay this <hi>Bathy</hi> was Father to <hi>Tamerlain,</hi> whom they call <hi>Temirkutla.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then ſucceeded <hi>Iaroſlaus</hi> Brother of <hi>George;</hi> and to him <hi>Alexander</hi> his Son. Then <hi>Daniel</hi> his Son, who firſt made <hi>Moſcow</hi> his Royal Seat, builded the Caſtle, and took on him the Title of great Duke, and was ſucceeded by <hi>John</hi> his Son Sirnam'd <hi>Kaleta</hi> or <hi>Scrip,</hi> as the word ſignifies, becauſe he uſually carryed one about him and dealt his Alms out of it to the poor. He left the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to <hi>John</hi> his Brother, and <hi>John</hi> left it to <hi>Demetrius</hi> his Son; who had two Sons <hi>Baſilius</hi> and <hi>George.</hi> The firſt Reigning had a Son, but doubting his Legitimacy, by reaſon of his Wives Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinency, he left his Brother to ſucceed him. But <hi>George</hi> dying pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered his Nephew, whoſe Name was <hi>Baſilius,</hi> before his own Sons <hi>Andrew</hi> and <hi>Demetrius,</hi> which occaſion'd much diſturbance in the State, for they wared on their Couzen, took him and put out his Eyes; yet the Nobles kept their Allegiance; and <hi>John Vaſilwich</hi> his Son ſucceeded him. This was he who by his Prudence and Valour firſt brought the Name of his Country out of obſcurity, and made it Renown'd in <hi>Europe</hi> and <hi>Aſia;</hi> Stileing himſelf great Duke of <hi>Volodimir, Moſcovy, Novogrod</hi> and <hi>CZAR</hi> of all <hi>Ruſſia;</hi> he won <hi>Ploſco,</hi> the then only Wall'd City in all <hi>Moſcovy,</hi> and ſhook off the <hi>Tartar</hi> Yoke, doing many other brave Exploits; ſo that the <hi>Poles,</hi> and bordering Nations on either ſide courted his Friendſhip.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gabriel</hi> his Son ſucceeded him, who changed his Name to <hi>Baſilius,</hi> he recover'd a great part of <hi>Moſcovy</hi> from <hi>Vitoldus</hi> Duke of <hi>Lithuania;</hi> won <hi>Smolensko</hi> and many other Citys, <hi>Anno.</hi> 1514.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:106947:15"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iuan Vaſiliwich</hi> his Son, a Child, ſucceeded him; but growing up, he ſtript the <hi>Tartars</hi> out of the Kingdoms of <hi>Cazan</hi> and <hi>Aſtracan,</hi> and took the Princes Captive; he made vigorous Wars in <hi>Livonia</hi> pretending a Right to that Country by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance; and did many other admirable things, but enclining much to oppreſs his Nobles, they conſpir'd and call'd in the <hi>Cri n Tartars,</hi> who committed great Outrages, Beſieged and burnt the City of <hi>Moſcow,</hi> and in it about 80000 people periſh'd, moſtly by the Flames. This Prince Reign'd 54 years, he had 3 Sons; in his Reign the <hi>Engliſh</hi> came the firſt time by Sea into the North parts of <hi>Ruſſia;</hi> his Eldeſt Son dyed before him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pheodor</hi> his Second Son ſucceeding, he was, being a Minor, left under the Tuition of <hi>Boris,</hi> Brother to the Empreſs, and <hi>Boris</hi> by the Deceaſed's Will adopted third Son to him; and here once for all it will not be amiſs to give a brief account of the Ceremony in Crowning this great <hi>CZAR.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Forty days Mourning for his Father expir'd, he came from his Pallace, attended by his Clergy and Nobility, to the Church of <hi>Blaueſhin,</hi> or <hi>Bleſſedneſs,</hi> and hearing Service there, proceeded to the Church of St <hi>Michael,</hi> then to that of our <hi>Lady,</hi> being the Cathedral. There he was plac'd in a Chair of State, his Robe of Gold-Smiths Work, all Gold, ſet with Pretious Stones and Pearl. The <hi>Imperial Crown</hi> was then plac'd on his head by the <hi>Metropolitan,</hi> who, in doing it, Read Exhortations to him of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Peaceable Government. Then riſing he was Inveſted with another Robe much Richer than the former; his Train born up by 6 Dukes, the Staff he held was of a <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorns-horn,</hi> 3 foot and a half long, curiouſly Poliſh'd, and ſet with Precious Stones; a Globe and 6 Crowns were carry'd before him by Princes of the Blood; His Horſe waited at the Church door, covered with an Embrodery of Pearl, and the Saddle ſuitable, to the value of 3000 <hi>Rubbles</hi> There was a kind of Bridge made 3 ways, 150 Fathom in length, 3 foot high and 2 Fathom broad, whereon the <hi>CZAR,</hi> with his Train paſſed from one Church to another above the vaſt throng of People. The Churches were ſpread with <hi>Cloath of Gold,</hi> and the Porches with <hi>Red Velvet.</hi> The Bridges with <hi>Scarlet,</hi> and <hi>Flannel Cloath,</hi> which the People got among them, when the <hi>CZAR</hi> had paſſed, and a great many new <hi>Coins of Gold and Silver</hi> were thrown among them, from the Church; the Cerimony ended, he return'd to the <hi>Parliament-Houſe,</hi> where a ſtately Banquet, after the <hi>Ruſs</hi> manner was ſerved up by Noblemen in Plate of <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Silver,</hi> 2 ſtanding on either ſide his Chair with <hi>Battle Axes</hi> of <hi>Gold.</hi> This Triumph laſted a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106947:16"/> Week with many Shows and Paſtimes; after which Election was made of the Nobles to new Offices and Dignities, and all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded with a peal of 170 Braſs Ordinance, and 20000 Harqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſſes twice diſcharged, as he paſs'd with a Train of about 50000 to his Pallace.</p>
               <p>This <hi>CZAR</hi> Conquer'd the large Country of <hi>Siberia,</hi> and took the King Priſoner, overawing the <hi>Tartars,</hi> and doing many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great matters: But <hi>Boris</hi> his Guardian aſpiring to the Throne by Treatchery, firſt made away <hi>Demetrius,</hi> the <hi>CZAR</hi>'s Brother, and then the <hi>CZAR</hi> himſelf, and uſurp'd the Royal Seat. But a Counterfit <hi>Demetrius,</hi> ſet up by the <hi>Poles</hi> Invading <hi>Moſcovy</hi> and every where prevailing, <hi>Boris,</hi> as 'tis thought, Poiſoned him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; for after a full Meal he dyed ſuddainly in his Pallace; and his Wife drinking Poiſon made her Son and Daughter pledge her, of which ſhe and the former dyed, but the latter only lightly ſipping recover'd.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Demetrius Evonowich</hi> hereupon was Proclaim'd and Crown'd, and kept about him <hi>Poliſh</hi>-Guards for his ſecurety, but had a ſhort and troubleſome Reign, for being ſuſpected an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſture, the <hi>Moſcovites</hi> Conſpired againſt him, ruſhed into his Pallace before break of day, draged him out of his Bed, and Slew him, with many of his Guards and Favorits.</p>
               <p>To him Succeeded <hi>Vaſily Evanowich Shusky,</hi> who had been mainly Inſtrumental in his deſtruction, and had not long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore been at the Block for reporting to have ſeen the True <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrius</hi> Bury'd; but he was recall'd by him he depos'd, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd to be the Inſtrument of his Ruin: It's reported the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtor's True Name was <hi>Gryfcha,</hi> the Son of a mean Gentleman. Nor did the New <hi>CZAR</hi> long hold the Throne, for the <hi>Poles</hi> raiſed up another <hi>Demetrius,</hi> who Beſieg'd him in the Caſtle of <hi>Moſcow,</hi> and wrought him Great Troubles; ſo that being hardly preſs'd, he betook him to a Monaſtery, and ſo the <hi>Poliſh</hi> Army became Maſter of the City; who having got the Spoil, Quarrel'd with their Upſtart <hi>Demetrius,</hi> and he flying to ſeek Shelter, was ſlain by a <hi>Tartar</hi>'s <hi>Shusk,</hi> who was carry'd into <hi>Poland,</hi> and there di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed miſerably in Priſon. Yet the <hi>Poles</hi> were ſoon after Starved, and driven out of all the places they had Garriſon'd in <hi>Moſcovy,</hi> and much Confuſion happen'd in this <hi>Interregnum,</hi> till at length ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Advice to ſettle matters, <hi>Michalowich,</hi> or <hi>Michael Pheodoro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich</hi> was Choſen <hi>CZAR,</hi> a Youth whom <hi>Shusky</hi> much feared, and had put ſeveral of the Name to Death, upon a Preſage one of that Name ſhould Succeed him; and having been Raiſed by the Valour of <hi>Pozarsky,</hi> and <hi>Boris Licin,</hi> he made them the Generals
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106947:16"/> of his Forces, and Joyn'd with them another Great Commander of the <hi>Coſſacks,</hi> who had very much Aſſiſted him, and rais'd to Honour many other of his Friends, ſo that ſoon after a Peace was Concluded between the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> and <hi>Poles,</hi> partly by the Mediation of King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt of <hi>England,</hi> he was Elected <hi>Anno</hi> 1615. and Manag'd his Dominions in a more conſtant way of Peace with the <hi>Turks, Tartars, Polanders</hi> and <hi>Swedes,</hi> than any of his Predeceſſors had done before him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Feodor Alexowitz,</hi> or <hi>Alexis,</hi> Succeeded him, who did ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny brave Actions, and ſecur'd his Borders againſt Invaders, and Reign'd to the Year 1682. Who then dying left Two Sons behind, <hi>John</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> who were Joynt-<hi>CZARS</hi> of <hi>Muſcovy</hi> till the firſt dying, the Whole Government devolved on the Latter, who now Reigns Succeſsfully and Victoriouſly, being a Wiſe and Judicious Prince, of a ſound diſcerning Judgement, Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and Affable, having Enlarg'd his Territories by the taking <hi>Aſoph,</hi> and giving the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars</hi> many Overthrows; his Underſtanding Refin'd, and much Improv'd by Learning and Travel; The Delight of Princes, and the Joy and Safety of his own People.</p>
               <p>THIS Princes Style is very Magnificent, <hi>viz. CZAR</hi> and Great <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>KE</hi> of all the <hi>Great and Leſſer White Ruſſia, Moſcovy, Kiovia, Volodomir, Novogrod;</hi> CZAR of <hi>Caſan;</hi> CZAR of <hi>Aſtracan;</hi> CZAR of <hi>Siberia,</hi> LORD of <hi>Plesko;</hi> Great DUKE of <hi>Smolensko, Twer, Inhor, Permo, Weſtquia, Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garia</hi> and others; LORD and Great DUKE of the Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour <hi>Novogrod,</hi> of <hi>Tzerni, Kiovia, Reſens, Roſtof, Jeroſlaw, Bielejezorvedor, Obdor, Condomir,</hi> and of all the Northern Part; LORD of <hi>Iberia;</hi> CZAR of <hi>Cartalania, Garſinea;</hi> DUKE of <hi>Cababadin;</hi> DUKE of the Dukes of <hi>Circaſſia</hi> and <hi>Georgia, and of ſeveral other Oriental, Septentrional, and Occidental Lordſhips and Eſtates;</hi> PATERNAL, Great PATERNAL Heir, SUCCESSOR, LORD aad RU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LER.</p>
               <p>The Great Seal of <hi>Moſcovy</hi> is an <hi>Eagle diſplayed Sable in a Field, Or, bearing on its Breaſt a Shield the Field being Gules, Charged with a St. George Argent, holding a Lance piercing a Dragon; between the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:106947:17"/> Heads of the Eagle</hi> are 3 Crowns placed, one over another, which are ſaid to ſignifie <hi>Moſcovy,</hi> and the two Kingdoms of <hi>Cazan</hi> and <hi>Aſtracan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Nobility of <hi>Moſcovy</hi> are of different Ranks, thoſe of the Antient Nobility, and ſuch as have been raiſed by Favour or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therways for their Noble Attchievements, <hi>viz.</hi> of four ſorts, The Chief for Birth Authority and Revenue are call'd <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>delney Knazey,</hi> that is, the Exempt or Priveledged Dukes. The ſecond, the <hi>Bojarens</hi> Rais'd to Honour by the <hi>CZAR,</hi> beſide their Nobility, with the Title of Counſelers. The Third are the <hi>Voyavodey,</hi> ſuch as have been Generals of Armys under their Prince. The Fourth are ſuch as bear the Name of <hi>Knazey,</hi> or Dukes, but come of the younger Brothers of the Chief Houſes through many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcents. And thus I doubt not but I have given a Satisfactory Account of this Fam'd Country.</p>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:106947:17"/>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
